<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations on the bill depending, for preventing occasional conformity humbly offered by the people called Quakers.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5912aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229791</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899370</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899370</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153139</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80364)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153139)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2350:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations on the bill depending, for preventing occasional conformity humbly offered by the people called Quakers.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>3,[1]p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing (CD-ROM edition) reports date of publication as [169?̲]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153139:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS ON THE BILL Depending, for Preventing <hi>Occaſional Conformity, <hi>Humbly Offered by the People called</hi>
               </hi> Quakers.</head>
            <p>IN the latter part of the Preamble of this Bill, it is declared, that the Act paſſed in the Firſt Year of the Reign of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Entituled, <hi>An Act for Exempting their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Proteſtant Subjects, Diſſenting from the Church of</hi> England, <hi>from the Penalties of certain Laws, ought</hi> Inviolably <hi>to be Obſerved.</hi> Which Noble Declaration, would give us Ground to hope that nothing is deſigned in this Bill, to Infringe the ſaid Act of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption; yet in the Beginning of the Preamble and following Clauſes of it, we have, as we humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, Reaſon to think the Liberty, given by the ſaid <hi>Act,</hi> is made liable to a Doubtful Senſe, <hi>if not Infringed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Firſt,</label> The Term <hi>[Truly]</hi> in the Preamble, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Limited in its acceptation, may be ſo conſtrued, as to interfer with the Deſign of the Act for Exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is therein declared to be to <hi>Unite</hi> the Queen's <hi>Proteſtant Subjects, in Intereſt and Affection;</hi> which good End, that Parliament did hope <hi>Effectually</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153139:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
by giving ſome Eaſe to <hi>Scrupulous Conſciences</hi> in the Exerciſe of Religion, as therein appears, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leaving it to any Subordinate Magiſtrate, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what is, or is not <hi>Truly Scrupulous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Secondly,</label> It ſeemed meet to that Parliament, not to diſtinguiſh the Religious Aſſemblies, or Meetings of Proteſtant Diſſenters, with the Term of <hi>Conventicles,</hi> as in this Bill, under which Term, by ſome former Laws, we have ſeverely ſuffered.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Thirdly,</label> To make any Perſon in Office, an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, and to forfeit his Office or Turſt, with a Penalty, only <hi>for Reſorting to, or being Preſent at</hi> any ſuch Aſſembly as aforeſaid, when the Occaſion may be on the account of a Funeral, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we conceive, if En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, will not only infringe the Toleration, but render Illegal the Common Offices of Love and Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity betwixt Friends and Relations, and not only to thoſe, who do Occaſionally Conform, but alſo to Conſtant Conformiſt<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Fourthly,</label> That Act allows ſundry Offices to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Deputy; this Bill makes no ſuch Proviſion, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept for Offices of Inheritance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Fifthly,</label> As we are Free-men of Corporations, and Members of Companies, by the Terms of Admiſſion, we are bound to do in our Courſe the ſeveral Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof; which by this Bill, we are not only ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred incapable of, but alſo ſubject to Fines and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties for not doing them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Sixthly,</label> The Words <hi>Scandalous and Irreligious Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices,</hi> uſed in this Bill, being in the Plural, ſeems to conclude the <hi>Reſorting to, or being Preſent at</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Meetings of Proteſtant Diſſenters, equally offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive with an Occaſional receiving of the Sacrament, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a Place of Profit, or Turſt in the Government, which we hope is not intended; for that would carry
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153139:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->an unmerited Reflection on Religious Aſſemblies, and is, as we conceive, not agreeable with the Act for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Seventhly,</label> we have never ſought after any Place of Profit or Truſt in the Government, and therefore pray that the Conſcientious Liberty, which we thankfully Enjoy, and was granted by that Act, may be kept entire.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Laſtly,</label> As it is our Chriſtian Principle to ſuffer for Conſcience, ſo the ſame makes us plead for the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, to all whoſe Morals and Obedience to the Government cannot Juſtly be queſtioned; and we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, reſtraining from <hi>Proving all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21.</note> in order to hold faſt that which may be moſt conducing to future Happineſs (the Chief End of <hi>RELIGION</hi>) is oppoſite to the Apoſtle's Advice; And where ſuch Reſtraint is, we cannot think the Toleration ſecure.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153139:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
